Alright, so I'll say it again for this—10th of November, it's the
21st of מרחשון, Marcheshvan, and today's דף daf will be מכות Makkot
דף ה. Daf He.
And yesterday we left off at the second משנה Mishnah on ה
עמוד א. He Amud Aleph. So we'll start from there. The משנה
Mishnah says, אין העדים נעשים זוממים עד שיזומו את עצמן. Ein ha-edim
na'asim zomemim ad she-yazumu et atzman. So this, this would have been
a good place to start in a sense because it actually introduces
us to the concept of עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, rather than teaching
us first all of the exceptions to עדים זוממים edim zomemim before
introducing the concept as a whole. But nonetheless, this is how רבי
Rebbi decided to organize the משניות. Mishnayos. So it says the witnesses
who are conspiring witnesses cannot be declared to be conspiratorial such that
they will receive this reciprocal punishment until their testimony is, is proven
to be conspiratorial through their own עד שיזומו את עצמן. ad she-yazumu
et atzman. They have to make themselves known to be conspiring, in
what way? So the משנה Mishnah says,
כיצד? Keitzad? אמרו מעידים אנו באיש פלוני שהרג את הנפש. Amru me'idim
anu be-ish ploni she-harag et ha-nefesh. They say, "We're testifying about so-and-so
that he killed someone." אמרו להם היאך אתם מעידים שהרי נהרג זה
או ההורג זה היה עמנו אותו היום במקום פלוני.
Amru lahem he'ich atem me'idim she-harei neherag zeh o ha-horeg zeh hayah
immanu oto
ha-yom bi-mkom ploni. So if other witnesses come and say that's impossible,
you can't be testifying to this murder because the murder victim or
the murderer—first the
question at the very beginning, the murder
victim—here
we go, it's right here in the משנה, Mishnah, the murder victim
or the murderer were with us in a different place at the
same time, אין אלו זוממים. Ein elu zomemim. Those are not עדים
זוממים. edim zomemim. It happens, turns out that we now have a
testimony that contradicts or undermines their testimony, but they're not, they're not
going to be executed for that. אבל אמרו להם היאך אתם מעידים
שהרי אתם הייתם עמנו אותו היום במקום פלוני. Aval amru lahem he'ich
atem me'idim she-harei atem hayitem immanu oto ha-yom bi-mkom ploni. If the
other witnesses come and say, "You witnesses were with us in a
different place on that day," הרי אלו זוממים. Harei elu zomemim. So
it's because their testimony is compromised by their own inability to have
actually witnessed this event. It's not to do with whether or not
they could have witnessed the murder, but specifically that they could not
have been there for it.
Well, he still could have been there for it if the נהרג
neherag was with the—wait, in the first case,
the murder victim—here we go, it's right here in the משנה, Mishnah,
the murder victim or the murderer were with us. No, but that's
undermining, did the murder take place or not, right? That's saying, "Oh,
the person who you're saying was murdered was with us at the
same time that you're claiming the murder took place." But the point
is that the עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, you witnesses could not have
witnessed what you claimed to have witnessed, not the thing you claimed
to have witnessed could not have happened. Those are two different kinds
of things, and we only care about the first one. הכחשה. Hakhashah.
הכחשה Hakhashah is contradiction, is proving the testimony false, right? So that
would be a claim, but that doesn't necessarily earn you the punishment
of עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. Okay.
באו אחרים והזימום. Bau acherim ve-hizimum. If other witnesses come and testify
about the second group of witnesses. באו אחרים והזימום, Bau acherim ve-hizimum,
or even now a fourth set of witnesses come and testify about
the third set of witnesses. אפילו מאה, Afilu me'ah, even a hundred
times. כולם יהרגו. Kulam yeiharegu.
All of them are put to death because they're all, except the
last set of witnesses obviously, because each time a different set of
witnesses has come and undermined their, their believability and their ability to
have testified to what they, to what they claimed to have testified,
so they're all part of this conspiracy. Okay, so רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagrees and he says,
well, it's just the end of the day, like what if it's
correct that this guy did kill somebody?
Right, it could be reversed multiple times, right, so you can have—right,
this is the original, I don't know how to, here—we're going to
have a
murderer killing somebody, okay? That's an arrow.
Are you going to teach you remedial...
right. And now we have the witnesses here, this is group number
one. Now group number two comes and
they
say, "Oh, עמנו הייתם." Immanu hayitem. So they make them זוממים. zomemim.
But then we can get a third group,
and they can come and say to them, עמנו הייתם Immanu hayitem
when you claimed עמנו הייתם Immanu hayitem about them, so then their
testimony will be true again, but it will jump many times back
and forth, back and forth, because you're each time undermining the chain
of believability going back.
Okay, but this says כולם יהרגו. Kulam yeiharegu. Right. Who is the
כולם? kulam?
Okay, so according to the תנא קמא Tanna kamma actually, everyone, because
they were part of a conspiracy, because these people said that you
were עמנו הייתם. Immanu hayitem.
Well, number two was lying though.
Well, we don't know, right? So at least according to—okay, so this
is part of, this is רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda objection. But at
least according to the תנא קמא, Tanna kamma, because everyone has some
flaw in their testimony, or at some point in the chain was
shown to have been flawed, even if it was by people who
may have been lying, but the point is that this whole system
creates,
undermines the testimony of all of them.
Okay, but this is specifically saying killing...
Right, so your objection is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*'s objection.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says what's the הוה אמינא hava
amina *havah amina* even? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says איסתטיידי
*istatidi*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to flesh it out
more, it might, it'll become more clear. Okay, so רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda אומר איסתטיידי זו *Rabbi Yehuda omer istatidi zo*, that's an איסתטית
*istatit*, it's some kind
of
a cabal, some kind of a conspiracy, that is each, each group
is part of a bigger conspiracy if they keep getting more people
to say, oh, you were wrong and you were wrong and you
were wrong. Therefore, ואינו נהרג אלא כת kat הראשונה בלבד bilvad. *ve'eino
neherag ela kat harishona bilvad*. Only the ones who actually came to
try to put this guy to death, that's why they're going to
be killed because their testimony was about the actual crime. But everyone
else is just somehow involved in a, in some tangential way. So
we don't care about it as much.
No, I'd say just the opposite, say the last ones, because we
know the last, you know, in other words, if no one came
and disputed the last ones, right?
Oh, we're going to see. The אמוראים Amora'im *Amoraim* are not happy
with this.
They're, you know, they're telling the truth, the last ones, at least
at this point, which means we don't know about anyone before, but
at least we know that, you know, number ten is saying that
number nine is lying, so we believe number ten as against number
nine. So I object. I say only the last ones.
So we're going to see how it comes up in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. Okay. So מנה הני מילי *mena hanei milei*? How do
we know this? So אמר רב אדא דאמר קרא והנה עד שקר
העד שקר ענה *Amar Rav Adda de'amar kra vehineh ed sheker ha'ed
sheker ana*. So the testimony is a false testimony. So עד שתשקר
גופא של עדות *ad shetishaker gufa shel edut*. The need is that
the lying, the falsehood, has to exist or occupy the space
of the core testimony.
So this is specifically why the falsehood has to be found about
where were these witnesses at the time when the crime took place
and could they have been witness to it or not? But not
that who was the person involved and where were they, you know,
those kinds of things. Oh, this person couldn't have been there is
not a good enough undermine of the testimony. דבי רבי Rebbi, ישמעאל
תנא לענות בו סרה עד שתסרה גופו של עדות *Debei Rabbi Yishmael
tanna la'anot bo sara ad shetisreh gufo shel edut*. Basically the same
idea learned from a different, a different part of the פרשה *parsha*
of עדים זוממים edim zomemim. *edim zomemim*. Okay.
אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava*, לסרה
*lesareh*, like לסור *lasur*, like to, to turn away. So the, until
it's been turned away. It's interesting because then the question becomes right
according to רב אדא *Rav Adda*, the emphasis is on the fact
that it's שקר *sheker*, and according to רבי Rebbi. ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*,
it's not so much, it doesn't have to be שקר *sheker*, total
falsehood, it has to be סרה *sara*, there has to be some
kind of a flaw, some kind of a turning aside within the
truth of this testimony, that's enough to undermine it. So he maybe
has a lower, a lower standard, maybe it's just a different דרשה
*drasha*. Anyway. Okay. אמר רבא Rava באו שנים ואמרו במזרח בירה הרג
hereg פלוני את הנפש *Amar Rava ba'u shenayim ve'amru bemizrach birah harag
ploni et hanefesh*. So two witnesses come and say on the eastern
side of this building, so and so killed someone. ובאו שנים ואמרו
והלא במערב בירה עמנו הייתם immanu hayitem *Uba'u shenayim ve'amru vehalo bema'arav
birah imanu heyitem*. And then two more witnesses say, oh, you were
on the western side of this building when you claim that this
murder took place.
So they couldn't have seen it.
So we say חזינן chazinan, אי כדקיימי במערב בירה מיחזי חזו למזרח
בירה *chazinan ei kedekaimei bema'arav birah michzei chazu lemizrach birah*. So we
can go and investigate whether you can see the eastern side of
the building from the western side of the building. So we say
אין אלו זוממין zomemin *ein elu zomemin*, then they won't be זוממין
*zomemin* because then it would be impossible, like it would have been
possible that they could see from the western side of the building
onto the eastern side of the building. ואם לאו הרי אלו זוממין
*Ve'im lav harei elu zomemin*. And if it's impossible to see from
side to side, then they are זוממין *zomemin*. So פשיטא pshita, *pshita*,
isn't that obvious that, oh, you should just investigate this question? So
מהו דתימא ליחוש לנהורא בריא *mahu deteima leichush lenahora barya*, we should,
we might have thought that we should be concerned about a case
where the witnesses had very good eyesight. קא משמע לן *ka mashma
lan*. So that's what this whole discussion is about, that actually we
are not concerned about superhuman vision. We go,
we assess the case based on the normal circumstance. What's interesting then
is you could have had witnesses who actually did see the murder,
right? Here's a building and the murder's over here and they're over
here and they have, you know, telescope, x-ray vision, they can see
through the building or something, or the windows lined up perfectly and
they, or something, there's a tiny little sliver that they just happened
to be standing exactly the right place or something, and we wouldn't
care. So we would kill these people and save this person's life
just because under normal circumstances, so again, maybe you have to investigate
more carefully or something like that, but it's an interesting question.
So it's interesting, I mean you could just say like you know,
maybe these guys have really good vision, just like put someone else
over there, let them like you know hold up how many fingers
do you see, they get it right then you know they could
have seen it. But we don't do that apparently.
We don't do that. We don't go back and revisit the case
so much, but here it's interesting that what we revisit is basically
would a normal person have been able to see this from this
position. Okay.
Do the judges go back there or go get witnesses?
I don't even think you need witnesses, they just sort of, I
don't know, I'm not sure. I'm not sure what it means. So
we go and see. Does it mean the judges have to go
investigate? Do they need to get witnesses about, I'm not sure, I'm
not sure. It doesn't say from the גמרא Gemara? *Gemara*, it just
says חזינן *chazinan*. We're able to see whether it's true or not.
So I don't know. ואמר רבא veamar Rava, באו שנים ואמרו בסורא
בצפרא בחד *Ve'amar Rava ba'u shenayim ve'amru beSura betzafra bechad*. So two
witnesses come and say in סורא, Sura,
on, in the morning, someone, on, on Sunday, Sunday morning in סורא,
Sura someone killed someone. ובאו שנים ואמרו בחד בשבתא עמנו הייתם בנהרדעא,
uvau shnayim veamru bechad beshabata
imanu hayitem benehardea,
and then two more people come and say back that on Sunday
you were with us in נהרדעא. Nehardea.
So חזינן, we go and see, is it possible to travel from
סורא Sura to נהרדעא Nehardea from the morning of one day until
the evening of the same day? לא הוו זוממים, lo havu zomemim,
so then they won't be זוממים. zomemim. ואי לאו הוו זוממים, vei
lav havu zomemim, if it's impossible to travel that distance, then they'll
be זוממים. zomemim. So פשיטא, pishita, so that's obvious. מהו דתימא ליחוש
לגמלא פרחא קא משמע לן, mahu deteima lichush legamla parcha ka mashma
lan, should we be concerned about the flying camel? This becomes the
source for all sorts of discussions about faster than camel travel, faster
than horse travel perhaps, but this is the גמרא Gemara here. I
think it comes up in the end of גיטין Gittin also, at
the end of סוטה, Sotah, something like that. It was over a
year ago in the דף, daf, two years ago, but so it
comes up every once in a while, this suggestion חז״ל Hazal were
aware perhaps theoretically of some sort of magic carpet, some sort of
faster than foot travel.
These things appear in the בבלי, Bavli, they don't appear in the
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
There you go, a little bit fanciful, but the idea is that
is there a, would we, should we be concerned about a very
rare occurrence that would have enabled them to be there? We say
no. These days it all goes away because the basic assumption is
there are all sorts of fast five hundred miles per hour travel
options. You take a train, you take a plane, you take even
driving, and it gets into interesting questions about like, oh, you know,
חז״ל Hazal measured time in distances, right? We measure, you know, how,
we say seventy-two minutes. Seventy-two minutes is the time it takes to
walk four מיל, mil, eighteen minutes or twenty-four minutes or whatever, you
know, these are measurements based on the walking
speed.
Light-year, same. Light-year. So the question becomes, for example, something like
washing your hands before תפילה, tefillah, you're supposed to, if it's four
מיל mil out of your way going forward and one מיל mil
out of your way behind you to return now, right? Does it
go by distance or does it go by time? So חז״ל Hazal
when they recorded those measurements talked about measurements
of distance. But if you drive now, to drive four מיל mil
is a short trip, so maybe we would be more מחמיר machmir
about those sort of things. It's an interesting question. Okay, sorry, I
lost the space. לגמלא פרחא קא משמע לן. legamla parcha ka mashma
lan. ואמר רבא, Rava באו שנים ואמרו בחד בשבתא הרג פלוני את
הנפש. bau shnayim veamru bechad beshabata harag ploni et hanefesh.
Two witnesses come and say on Sunday, so-and-so killed someone. ובאו שנים
ואמרו עמנו הייתם בחד בשבתא, uvau shnayim veamru imanu hayitem bechad beshabata,
and two more witnesses come and say you were with us on
Sunday, we had a barbecue. אלא בתרי בשבתא הרג פלוני את הנפש,
ela betrei beshabata harag ploni et hanefesh,
but we, the second set of witnesses, actually know that the same
person committed a murder, the murder that you thought happened on Sunday,
which you're falsely claiming and we can prove that you were lying,
but actually he killed him on Monday. Okay, okay, so what do
we say? בחד בשבתא, bechad beshabata, בתרי בשבתא הרג פלוני את הנפש,
betrei beshabata harag ploni et hanefesh, ולא עוד אלא אפילו אמרו ערב
שבת הרג פלוני את הנפש, velo od ela afilu amru erev shabbat
harag ploni et hanefesh, even if they say he killed him on
Friday and you were with us on Sunday, that is the distance
between the days could be multiple days, it could be, you know,
six days later or something like that. Nonetheless, נהרגין, דבעידנא דקסהדי גברא
לאו בר קטלא הוא,
neheragin debeidna dekasahadei gavra lav
bar katala hu. because at the time that he testified, that is
the time that these people testified, they were, their testimony was going
to be what killed this person. Right? So they'll be killed even
though this person is still going to get the death penalty for
the murder because this person committed murder. These two witnesses testified that
he committed murder, but we as if split the testimony to two
parts. Number one part is these are עדים זוממים. edim zomemim Number
two is that this guy actually is a murderer, he just killed
someone on a different day. Yeah. What about the פשט pshat of
אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi appearing and resurrected the guy? We don't say
that. If we're not worried about
the גמלא פרחא, gamla parcha, we're not going to be worried about
that.
Okay, נהרגין neheragin, דבעידנא דקסהדי גברא לאו בר קטלא הוא.
debeidna dekasahadei gavra lav
bar
katala hu, So מאי קא משמע לן תנינא? mai ka mashma lan
tanina?
So what's this משנה mishna come to teach us?
So we have a משנה mishna that's quoted from tomorrow's דף. daf.
לפיכך נמצאת אחת מהם זוממת, lephichach nimtset achat mehem zomemet, so therefore
one of the two groups of witnesses will be found to have
been conspiring, הוא והן נהרגין, hu vehen neheragin, he and the witness,
that is the murderer and the witnesses will both be executed, והשנייה
פטורה, vehashniya petura, but the second group of witnesses will be off
the hook. So סיפא, seifa, so what about the סיפא? seifa? מה
שאין כן בגמר דין, ma sheein ken begmar din, so what isn't
so in the final verdict. It does not apply if there had
already been a גמר דין gemar din about the murder case, that
is, if the murder case had already been finalized, then why is
that? Okay, so איצטריכא ליה, itstrikhah lei, we need it to teach
us this case. באו שנים ואמרו באחד בשבת נגמר דינו של פלוני,
bau shenayim ve-amru be-ehad be-shabbat nigmar dino shel ploni, two witnesses come
and say on Sunday there was the גמר דין, gemar din, the
final verdict for this case. Okay, ובאו שנים ואמרו באחד בשבת עמנו
הייתם, u-bau shenayim ve-amru be-ehad be-shabbat immanu hayitem, and then two more
people come and testify that you were actually with us somewhere else.
אלא בערב שבת נגמר דינו, ela be-erev shabbat nigmar dino, but the
court case actually was finalized on Friday, נגמר דינו של פלוני, nigmar
dino shel ploni, ולא עוד אלא אפילו אמרו בשני בשבת, ve-lo od
ela afilu amru be-sheni be-shabbat, and even if they claimed it was
on Monday, נגמר דינו של פלוני, nigmar dino shel ploni, that Ploni's
court case was a final verdict, אין אלו נהרגין. ein elu neheragin.
Then these for such a case if the גמר דין gemar din
was already finalized, they, the זוממים zomemim who have been proven to
have been conspiring, right? They could not have been there at the
time that the גמר דין gemar din happened. Why? דבעידנא דקמסהדי גברא
בר קטלא הוא, de-be-idna de-ka-mashadi gavra bar katla hu, because at the
time that they're testifying about, he was already a convicted, he was
already, it was already the גמר דין, gemar din, he's already a
dead man walking. That is what, they're only, they're not testifying about
a crime, they're testifying that the verdict was issued from the court.
So that's, that has no effect. Oh, you testify that such and
so verdict was finalized. Okay. So to that's not something that's going
to kill this person. This person was already going to be killed
for something else, for what the court had already determined based on
the testimony of other witnesses. So the fact that these witnesses prove
them to be זוממים zomemim is not going to give them the
death penalty because they weren't, but that's also פשיטא, אפילו שזוממים, afilu
she-zomemim, they weren't trying to, they weren't conspiring to kill this guy.
So why would these guys be killed? So it's obvious also. Right.
Okay. No?
Am I not getting something? Well, because maybe the guy hasn't been
killed yet, right? He's still on death row or whatever.
So maybe he would be, maybe something got lost, something
got confused, and now
we're relying on the testimony here, they saying, oh, in this other
בית דין beit din his verdict was, was issued. So it's not
only that their testimony is not what, what gives the power to
kill him, but it's that
the ruling of the court is what, what creates the death sentence.
Right? At some point the power, the locus of the, of the
punishment shifts from the witnesses to the court. That's the גמר דין.
gemar din. So once the גמר דין gemar din takes place, no
longer are the witnesses the one who are responsible for the fact
that he's going to be executed. At that point, the, the consequence
is now no longer be due to their testimony. So even, right.
So the guy runs away, let's say.
The guy runs away and now you find him on the street,
and
these guys say, oh, you know, you, oh, we were
in
Kansas City, we saw in the בית דין beit din in Kansas
City that they voted that he's, that he's getting הרג tomorrow.
So they would kill him based on those guys' testimony.
I would think so, under a normal case. And then the fact
that they're proven זוממים zomemim though, is not enough to kill them
because actually their testimony is not affecting the, the execution in the
same way.
What is the point of their even making that testimony?
To, to get him to be
executed. That's the מחייב. mehayyev. Meaning, suppose the murderer runs away.
They didn't know that he was already, the other, the
second בית דין beit din doesn't know, right? It's some other בית
דין. beit din. He ran away to a different city or something
like that, for example.
They're not really proven them זוממים, zomemim, right? Because they're just saying
it happened on a different day. They're not saying, right?
No, but they say עמנו הייתם on the day that you claim.
That's the זוממים zomemim step. The other step is, oh, and also
we're testifying that actually the thing that you claim happened did happen,
but it happened on a different day. They say both things.
Okay.
So what where the, where the זוממים zomemim testify that this guy
has already been convicted in San Francisco.
Yeah.
And
the court in New York is now willing to execute him
based on, right, based on the ruling of the other court, which
has been relayed to them by the testimony of these witnesses. Right.
But then if the second group comes and says, but the first
group was in New York, how could they know what the San
Francisco court
had had ruled, right?
Even though the defendant was already convicted by the first
court,
if the, if the first set of witnesses couldn't have known
that.
Yeah. It seems like the New York court has no basis.
No, but again, remember, the second set of witnesses say, and his
דין din was נגמר דינו nigmar dino on
Monday or on Friday. Their second half is testifying about the facts
of the case
happened,
it happened on a different day. So the point is, if they
testify, if they testify, oh, you killed someone on Sunday, and then
they come say, you were with us on Sunday, but the same
person killed the same
person. The point is that here the difference is that they're not
testifying about the murder, they're testifying about the גמר דין. gmar din.
They're testifying about the גמר דין; gmar din; it's enough to be
able to kill him one degree separation from the first set of
witnesses to kill this person.
This is like a Shakespearean play.
There you go. Okay, okay. And more a little bit more practically.
Now again, it's also interesting, a little detail that maybe we missed
is that רבא Rava was talking about what if a murder takes
place in סורא Sura and the witnesses were in נהרדעא. Nehardea. Those
are in בבל. Bavel. Did they ever do דיני נפשות dinei nefashot
in בבל? Bavel? Interesting question. Okay.
And could they ever have even—they can't
even do דיני קנסות dinei knasot in בבל. Bavel.
Okay, so this becomes an interesting question. Why is רבא rava using
examples like סורא and נהרדעא? Nehardea?
Like, you know, oh okay,
Kansas City and New York, right. But it becomes—it's interesting. Okay, they
probably did דיני נפשות dinei nefashot in בבל Bavel before the חורבן.
churban. I don't know. Okay, וכן לעניין תשלומי קנס. v'chen l'inyan tashlumei
knas. And the same principle applies to תשלומי קנס, tashlumei knas, that
is paying a—to pay a קנס, knas, the same principle that if
the קנס knas has already
been, I don't know the words for this in English, like the
court mandates that the person pay the fine, they issue the fine.
At that point, it's like a גמר דין, gmar din, it's like—so
it becomes no longer that the witnesses are testifying about the crime,
now they're just testifying about the ruling of the court. תבאו שנים
ואמרו בחד בשבת גנב וטבח ומכר. tavu shnayim v'amru b'chad b'shabbat ganav
v'tavach u'machar. So like the following example: two witnesses come and say
so and so stole somebody's cow and slaughtered it or sold it,
and that's going to incur the payments of ד' וה'. daled v'hei.
For a cow it should be
ד'. daled. No,
ה'. hei. ה' hei for a cow, only ד' daled for a
sheep, ד' daled for a sheep. ובאו שנים ואמרו בחד בשבת עמנו
הייתם. u'vau shnayim v'amru b'chad b'shabbat imanu heyitem. And then two more
witnesses come and say that actually on Sunday you were with us.
אלא בטר בשבת גנב וטבח ומכר משלמין ולא עוד אלא אפילו אמרו
בערב שבת גנב וטבח ומכר משלמין. ela b'trei b'shabbat ganav v'tavach u'machar
m'shalmin v'lo od ela afilu amru b'erev shabbat ganav v'tavach u'machar m'shalmin.
So
and even if they say it was even on Friday, but the
point is that the same witnesses have now instead of a murder,
he killed the cow or he sold the cow, so the fine
will be paid. Why? דבעידנא דקא מסהדי גברא, d'beidana d'ka mashadi gavra,
that
at the time that they מסהדי, mashadi, at the time that they
testified, גברא לאו בר תשלומין הוא. gavra lav bar tashlumin hu. At
the time that they're testifying, he's not yet been declared to be
someone who is obligated to pay this fine. But ובאו שנים ואמרו
בחד בשבת גנב וטבח ומכר ונגמר דינו, u'vau shnayim v'amru b'chad b'shabbat
ganav v'tavach u'machar v'nigmar dino,
they testify on Sunday in such and such a court this person's
case was concluded and he was determined to be someone liable to
pay this fine. ובאו שנים ואמרו בחד בשבת עמנו הייתם, u'vau shnayim
v'amru b'chad b'shabbat imanu heyitem, and then two more witnesses come and
testify you were with us on Sunday. אלא ערב שבת גנב וטבח
ומכר נגמר דינו ולא עוד. ela erev shabbat ganav v'tavach u'machar nigmar
dino v'lo od. Okay, so and then you're testifying actually on Friday
he did it
and the court case was finalized on Friday. ולא עוד אלא אפילו
אמרו בחד בשבת וטבח ומכר בחד ובטר בשבת נגמר דינו, v'lo od
ela afilu amru b'chad b'shabbat v'tavach u'machar b'chad u'v'trei b'shabbat nigmar dino,
and they say that actually the court case was finalized on Monday.
אין משלמין, ein m'shalmin, they don't pay. דבעידנא דקא מסהדי, d'beidana d'ka
mashadi, at the time that they're testifying about, that is the time
of the גמר דין, gmar din, גברא בר תשלומין הוא, gavra bar
tashlumin hu, he's already become a בר תשלומין. bar tashlumin. That is
the criminal, the defendant, has been slotted into the punishment already. At
that point, no longer is it due to the witnesses that the
punishment is going to take effect, it's because of the ruling of
the court and they're just testifying about the facts of the case,
about did such and such court issue such and such a ruling.
So no longer is it through the testimony of the witnesses that
the punishment is being effected and therefore they can't receive that punishment
in reciprocity for having been זוממים. zomemim. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר אסטטית
היא זו. Rabbi Yehuda omer istatit hi zu. So what is this
אסטטית? istatit? Okay.
And Gloria, you said up to the second משנה mishna or up
to the first משנה? mishna?
Up to the second משנה. mishna.
Okay, so that's good, we have time. Okay. אי אסטטית היא זו
אפילו כת ראשונה נמי. ei istatit hi zu afilu kat rishona nami.
So if you say it's an אסטטית, istatit, then you should say
even the first כת kat should also not be killed. That is,
if you say this whole קהל, kahal, it's a whole conspiracy and
everyone in multiple sets of witnesses are all tied up in this
together and we shouldn't kill anybody, then as soon as there are
multiple sets of זוממים, zomemim, then we shouldn't kill anybody according to
this objection of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda Okay. So אמר
רבי אבא הוא שקדמו והרגו. amar Rabbi Abba hu shekadmu v'haregu. No,
it must be in a case where based on the testimony of
the first witnesses, they already had executed the murderer. And now the
עדים זוממים edim zomemim are coming later. So מאי דהוה הוה. mai
d'hava hava. So we say wait a second, if they already killed
someone, so then it's already done. So we can't go back and
reevaluate. Or we
can't—not that we can't go back and kill him again, but we
can't—no, then we kill the witnesses, right.
These witnesses came and they were זוממים zomemim and so we killed
them. And then later people came and testified about them that they're
זוממים, zomemim, you say ah, מאי דהוה הוה, mai d'hava hava, these
people are already dead. Okay. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, what
does רבא say? הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, אם אינו אלא כת אחת
נהרגת. im eino ella kat achat neherget. If it's only one כת
of witnesses, then they'll be killed. Okay. אי איכא טפי אין נהרגין.
ei ika tfei ein nehergin. But that רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position
is that if there is one set of witnesses, then we'll kill
them. But that is two sets of witnesses, one set of זוממין
and one set of מזימין. mazimim. But if there are multiple sets,
multiple קיטות kitot of עדים, edim, then we don't kill anybody. So
הא בלבד אמר, ha bilvad amar, but he said בלבד. bilvad? He
said so why did he say the word
בלבד? bilvad. So קשיא. kashya.
I understand the answer. Let's suppose that's the case. The case is
that there's like many people and רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda responding.
Well, there are multiple sets of witnesses, right?
The case of the משנה Mishnah
was באו אחרים והזימום ובאו אחרים והזימום אפילו מאה כולם יהרגו. bau
acherim vehizimum uvau acherim vehizimum afilu meah kulam yehergu. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says, you know, so...
right, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. says בלבד. bilvad, So the point
is that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. says בלבד, bilvad, so it sounds
like there were multiple cases. So that's קשיא, kashya, we leave that
question as unanswered.
No, no, no, but meaning like, it's like meaning that the case
of the משנה Mishnah was that there are hundreds of them, and
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda responding to that, okay?
So like, yeah, רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda? responding to that.
So what's the answer the גמרא Gemara gives?
There is no answer though, leave it as a קשיא. kashya.
No, no, but what's the גמרא?
רבא's answer is if there were only one set of witnesses, then
נהרגין. nehergin. That is, there were two sets of witnesses, one to
be מזיים mazim the other. And if there are multiple ones, then
they won't be killed.
None of them?
None of them, according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. And then we
say, oh, but wait a second, it says בלבד, bilvad so it
says we only kill the first set, so that sounds like there
must be, kill the first set in a case where there are
others. Now you could say, and again קשיא kashya is sort of
not always such a strong answer, which is that, oh yeah, בלבד
bilvad. because there's a second set. We would have had no reason
to kill these people because there is no third set of witnesses,
right? There are just two sets of witnesses, two and one. But
so these people are enough to execute these people. We say we
kill the first one בלבד. bilvad So still the בלבד is not
so גלאט, glatt, but...
but I still don't understand my question. Why do you kill the
last one? Just the last one. In other words, we don't, in
the whole, we don't know everyone's like...
that's a different way to understand רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda But he
says ראשונה. rishona. I don't know, I haven't looked into it. I
didn't look into it. It's a good question. Not sure. Presumably because
we think once there's so many different back and forth about these
witnesses, now we're starting to get suspicious. Like what's going on?
No, but I understand that. We're suspicious about everyone else because like
you know who knows, but then but no one... this proves the
last set. So as far as we know, based on you know
the way we set up our system, they're telling the truth, right?
I guess, I don't know.
Don't know about everyone else because we can't trust anyone else by
now. But we know that the last ones are lying, based on
the
second to last one though,
so I don't know.
It's a good question, I'm not sure. I'll have to look into
it. Okay, ההיא אתתא דאתו סהדי. hahu itata de'atai sahadé. There was
a woman that witnesses came...
wait, I've got a little note here, I don't know if this
helps, but suggests the actual answer is that the citation of רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda statement on our משנה Mishnah is somewhat inaccurate. It
needs to be amended to read they are not executed unless the
הזמה hazamah witnesses discredit only the first set of witnesses alone.
Does that help? I'm not sure it helps. I'll have to research
a little bit more. It's a bit of an interesting question. Doesn't
seem to be what the גמרא is interested in, which is why
it's a good question, whatever, takes further research. Okay, ההיא אתתא דאתו
סהדי. hahu itata de'atai sahadé.
So there was a woman about whom witnesses came to
testify, ואשתקור, veishtakur, and they became proven to be lying. רש״י Rashi
says אשתקור הכחישו זה את זה. ishtakur hikh'shishu ze et ze. The
sets of witnesses were disagreeing or contradicting each other בדרישות, bidrishot, דרישות
בית דין. drishot beit din. So when the court is cross-examining the
witnesses...
when the court is cross-examining the witnesses,
the witnesses are shown to contradict each other. אתו סהדי ואשתקור. atai
sahadé veishtakur. So and so they brought further witnesses about this case
and they were also shown to be contradicting each other. אזלה, azlah,
so she left. אתו סהדי אחריני atai sahadé achrinei and she brought
more witnesses דלא אשתקור delo ishtakur who didn't contradict each other. אמר
ריש לקיש הוחזקה זו. Amar Reish Lakish huchzekah zo. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says in such a case now she's already been shown that
this case that she's trying to bring witnesses about is a case
about whom the witnesses are all contradicting each other, it sounds like
we're already suspicious. Already twice that we're suspicious.
So like you know the
third time she briefs the witnesses first and says okay give the
same answer to the questions and then already it was too late.
Doesn't it also depend on the חזקה chazakah two or three?
Right, it also depends on the חזקה chazakah two or three. So
here it sounds like according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish it's enough
to have a חזקה chazakah of two. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi
Elazar, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says
back, אם היא הוחזקה כל ישראל מי מוחזקו? im hi huchzekah kol
yisrael mi michuzku? So if she's הוחזקה huchzekah then but still meaning
that we would still be suspicious about
are we going to really question we're going to doubt the testimony
that every single... they're different people, they're different testimony. We're going to
say that these witnesses are assumed to be lying just because the
woman who they're testifying about we have suspicions about? We shouldn't be
suspicious of these witnesses because then you're going to cast every every
witness's reliability into doubt. זימנין הוה יתיב קמיה דרבי יוחנן. zimnin hava
yativ kamei deRabbi Yochanan. There was a time when they were sitting
before רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אתיא כי האי מעשה לקמיה. ata ki
hai maise lekameih. Who such a case came before רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, so it's interesting we're... So it's interesting, we're dealing with now
all different אמוראים of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. So אמר
ריש לקיש amar Reish Lakish הוחזקה זו. hukzeka zo. So ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish said, oh, she's מוחזקה mukhzeka already to be to be
tampering with the witnesses. אמר ליה רבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rabbi Yochanan,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said back to ריש לקיש: Reish Lakish: אם
הוחזקה זו כל ישראל הוחזקו. im hukzeka zo kol Yisrael huhzaku. So
that must be where רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar got it from. So
הדר חזייה לרבי אלעזר בבישות, hadar hazya le-Rabbi Elazar be-bishut, so they
saw that
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar was embarrassed.
Was he embarrassed? Why was
he
embarrassed?
I'm not sure why he would be
embarrassed. One second. החזיר ריש
לקיש פניו.
hehzir
Reish
Lakish panav. Oh, no. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar saw חזייה לרבי אלעזר
hazya le-Rabbi Elazar that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is upset that ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish is upset because what happened? Because רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish had a מחלוקת machloket and then
they asked it to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So החזיר ריש, hehzir
Reish, look at רש"י, Rashi, החזיר ריש לקיש את פניו ונסתכל ברבי
אלעזר בפנים זעופות, hehzir Reish Lakish et panav ve-nistakel be-Rabbi Elazar be-fanim
ze'ufot, so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was upset and he glared at
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar שהבין ריש לקיש ששמע רבי אלעזר דבר זה
מפי רבי יוחנן וכשאמרו לו לא אמרו בשמו. she-hevin Reish Lakish she-shama
Rabbi Elazar davar zeh mi-pi Rabbi Yochanan u-keshe-amro lo lo amro bi-shemo.
So he's upset because ריש לקיש Reish Lakish learned so much of
his תורה Torah from רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, again, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish often disagrees with רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, but at least in this case it sounds like ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish would have been willing to disagree with רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, but had he heard this הלכה halakha from רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, he would have retracted his opinion. So here he's upset that
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar did not quote רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and
therefore
he didn't know that
it was his own opinion. Right. So רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is
embarrassed that he is בבישות, be-bishut,
meaning ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was looking at him in a disparaging
way.
But רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is now upset because what happened? He
didn't quote רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan for this הלכה. halakha. Okay. So
אמר ליה, amar lei, he says to him: שמעת מילי מבר נפחא?
shamat mili mi-bar Nafha? So he says, I heard it from, you
know, from somebody else, from, you know, from outside. ולא אמרת לי
משמיה. ve-lo amart li mi-shmeh. So I didn't hear it in the
name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. And בר נפחא, bar Nafha, from
a blacksmith?
No, you're, you know, he's looking at רבי אלעזר: Rabbi Elazar: שמעת
מילי מבר נפחא, shamat mili mi-bar Nafha, you heard this from רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ולא אמרת לי משמיה? ve-lo amart li mi-shmeh? And
you didn't tell me
it was from רבי יוחנן?
Rabbi Yochanan? How could you?
Right. Right. Better. So לימא ריש לקיש דאמר כרבי יהודה? leima Reish
Lakish de-amar ke-Rabbi Yehuda? Maybe ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish opinion is just
like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda ורבי יוחנן דאמר כרבנן? ve-Rabbi Yochanan de-amar
ke-rabanan? And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying like רבנן, rabanan, and
it's just a מחלוקת machloket based on our
משנה. mishna. אמר לך ריש לקיש: amar lakh Reish Lakish: אנא דאמרי
לך אפילו רבנן. ana de-amri lakh afilu rabanan. So what will ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish say? אמר לך ריש לקיש, amar lakh Reish Lakish,
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish can defend himself and say: אנא דאמרי לך,
ana de-amri lakh, that what I'm saying, אפילו רבנן, afilu rabanan, my
opinion is even within the רבנן's rabanan position. הכא לא קאמרי רבנן
התם, hacha lo kaamri rabanan hatam, so in our משנה mishna the
רבנן's rabanan position that is we would kill all of the multiple
כיתות kitot of
witnesses, right? Okay. אמר לו אפילו רבנן הכא לא קאמרי רבנן התם
דאיכא הדרא amar lo afilu rabanan hacha lo kaamri rabanan hatam de-ika
hadara because you can't go back, אבל הכא, aval hacha, in our
case, the case of the woman with the multiple sets of witnesses,
איכא דקא מהדר, ika de-ka mahadar, it's possible to go back on
it because it's not because because we're not going to investigate we
could investigate these witnesses more, find out more, we still have the
דרישות drishot available to us. רבי יוחנן אמר לך: Rabbi Yochanan amar
lakh: אנא דאמרי אפילו רבי יהודה. ana de-amri afilu Rabbi Yehuda. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan will say my opinion is even according to
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda, הכא לא קאמר רבי יהודה התם דאמרי אתו
כולי עלמא. hacha lo ka-amar Rabbi Yehuda hatam de-amri atu kulei alma.
So רבי יהודה's position in the משנה mishna was only when it
was applying to
everyone. So לגבי הני הוו קיימי, legabei hanei havu kaimei, in this
case they're already like in front of us. אבל הכא, aval hacha,
in our case, הני ידעי בסהדותא, hanei yad'ei be-sahaduta, we already know
about these witnesses and about the testimony. והני לא ידעי בסהדותא, ve-hanei
lo yad'ei be-sahaduta, and the fact is that they're contradicting each other
in the דרישות. drishot. So it's clear that who who was aware
of the testimony and who was not. So it's not a case
where we have no information about the different groups of witnesses, we've
actually reached a point where we have other information that's causing us
to be suspicious and that's why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say
even according to רבי יהודה we would be more suspicious about the
later witnesses. Okay. Next משנה. mishna. אין עדים זוממים נהרגים עד שיגמר
הדין. ein edim zomemim neheragim ad she-yigamer ha-din. The עדים זוממים edim
zomemim should not be executed until the גמר דין gmar din has
been issued. שהרי הצדוקים אומרים עד שיהרג. sheharei ha-Tzedukim omrim ad she-yehareg.
The צדוקים Tzedukim say we don't provide the reciprocal capital punishment for
עדים זוממים edim zomemim unless the defendant has actually been executed. The
rabbinic tradition is not that. The rabbinic tradition is only between if
they're proven to have been זוממים zomemim between the גמר דין gmar
din and before the defendant has been
executed. Okay. So שהרי הצדוקים אומרים עד שיהרג שנאמר נפש תחת נפש,
sheharei ha-Tzedukim omrim ad she-yehareg shene'emar nefesh tahat nafesh, because they quote
the פסוק pasuk that you take a life for a life. They
killed him, so then they should be killed reciprocally. Okay. אמרו להם
חכמים. amru lahem hakhamim. So the rabbinic rabbis return to the צדוקים
Tzedukim and say: והלא כבר נאמר ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו.
ve-halo kvar ne'emar ve-asitem lo ka-asher zamam la-asot le-ahiv. The פסוק pasuk
says you have to do according to what the conspiracy was against
against his colleague, against his friend. והרי אחיו קיים. ve-harei ahiv kayyam.
The point is that the friend is still the brother is still
alive. אם כן למה נאמר נפש תחת נפש, Im ken lama ne'emar
nefesh tachas nefesh, so why does the פסוק pasuk say a life
for a
life? יכול משקיבלו עדותם יהרגו. Yachol mishe'kiblu edusam yeihareigu. So משקיבלו עדותן
יהרגו mishe'kiblu edusan yeihareigu to suggest to you no, you can't that
we shouldn't execute them from the time of the קבלת עדות. kabbalas
edus. So we have time points, קבלת עדות, kabbalas edus, then we
have the גמר דין, gmar din, and then
we have the הריגה. hariga. So the point is that חכמים chachamim
say during this period is when you could have זוממים, zomemim, but
not here. Okay, not between the קבלת עדות kabbalas edus and the
גמר דין. gmar din. So that's what נפש תחת נפש nefesh tachas
nefesh teaches you is not here because they weren't the life wasn't
yet forfeit yet.
And the צדוקים Tzedukim are to the right.
Right, the צדוקים Tzedukim say only we'll say the צדוקים Tzedukim are
over here.
So at the moment nobody is to the left of that.
Right, but this is the הוה אמינא that the פסוק pasuk נפש
תחת נפש nefesh tachas nefesh comes to reject. Okay, משקיבלו עדותן יהרגו?
mishe'kiblu edusan yeihareigu? תלמוד
לומר Talmud lomar נפש תחת נפש. nefesh tachas nefesh. הא
אינן נהרגין עד שיגמר הדין. Ha einan nehareigin ad sheyigmar hadin. So
the point is that you only kill this person until the גמר
דין. gmar din. What's fascinating about this is actually that it's very
much in conversation with other משניות mishnayos about the significance of the
גמר דין gmar din for a person's status as quote unquote a
dead man walking. I gave a דבר תורה dvar Torah about this
a few years ago. The משניות mishnayos in ערכין Arachin and in
other places discuss what if someone takes a ערך erech for themselves
from between their גמר דין gmar din as they're going to be
executed. And the point is that such a case, and there's a
little bit of a מחלוקת machlokes about it or different ways to
read the משנה, mishnah, but basically that at such a point in
many ways a person is already their life is forfeit and in
other ways not necessarily. So but the point is that the sense
that the גמר דין gmar din already creates a legal status of
dead man walking in a way that has consequences like for here
that we say, oh, that's enough to make it so that these
people get the capital punishment. If this person already gets executed, after
the execution, the case is already totally finished. We can't go back
and revisit the testimony anymore. So that's what's interesting about this principle.
Okay, so the גמרא says תני בריבי. tana be-ribbi. בריבי Be-ribbi said
אומר לא הרגו נהרגין. omer lo haragu nehareigin. If they didn't kill
him, then they'll be executed. הרגו אין נהרגין. haragu ein nehareigin. If
they killed him, then they shouldn't be executed. אמר אביו. amar aviv.
So his father says, so בריבי be-ribbi is probably רבי יהודה the
son of רבי, which is why I forget or there's a bit
of some kind of a מחלוקת machlokes about who he is, but
his father is רבי. So he says אמר אביו, amar aviv, בני,
beni, לאו קל וחומר הוא? lav kal vachomer hu? Is it not
a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? So אמר לו, amar lo, לימדתנו רבינו.
limadetanu rabbeinu. Didn't teacher, didn't you teach me, that is my father
רבי יהודה, רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, why didn't you didn't
you teach me שאין עונשין מן הדין, she'ein onshin min hadin, that
we can't punish people based on a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? דתניא
de-tanya איש אשר יקח את אחותו בת אביו או בת אמו, ish
asher yikach es achoso bas aviv o vas imo, a man who
has a sexual relationship with his father's daughter or his mother's daughter,
אין לי אלא בת אביו שלא בת אמו ובת אמו שלא בת
אביו. ein li ela bas aviv shelo vas imo uvas imo shelo
vas aviv. I could only infer from this either a paternal sister
who is not a maternal sister, that is only half sisters.
ובת אמו ובת אביו מניין. uvas imo uvas aviv minayin. So how
do I know that a full sister you also would be executed
for it? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar ערות אחותו גילה, ervas achoso gila,
that he uncovered his sister's nakedness. עד שלא יאמר. ad shelo yomar.
So why does the תורה Torah have to be explicit about that?
It must prove that's the principle that שאין עונשין מן הדין, she'ein
onshin min hadin, that we can't execute someone just based on a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. עד שלא יאמר ad shelo yomar יש לי
בדין. yesh li badin. So that you can't say oh I could
just derive it from קל וחומר. kal vachomer. אם ענש על בת
אביו שלא בת אמו ובת אמו שלא בת אביו. im anash al
bas aviv shelo vas imo uvas imo shelo vas aviv. בת אביו
ובת אמו לא כל שכן? bas aviv uvas imo lo kol sheken?
So couldn't I have learned it from קל וחומר kal vachomer that
if a half sister I would be executed for then a full
sister by קל וחומר. kal vachomer. הא לא ענש אלא שאין עונשין
מן הדין. ha lo anash ela she'ein onshin min hadin. So I
learn that this way. So עונש שמענו. onesh shamanu. אזהרה מניין. azhara
minayin. So that's where I learn about the עונש, onesh, the actual
punishment. But אזהרה, azhara, right? Because every capital crime has to be
mentioned twice in the תורה, Torah, once for the punishment and once
for the prohibition. So מניין. minayin. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar ערות אחותך
בת אביך או בת אמך. ervas achosecha bas avicha o vas imecha.
So the פסוק pasuk also says the nakedness of your sister who
is either your father's daughter or your mother's daughter. אין לי אלא
בת אביו שלא בת אמו ובת אמו שלא בת אביו. ein li
ela bas aviv shelo vas imo uvas imo shelo vas aviv. I
would only think a half sister, either paternal or maternal. בת אביו
ובת אמו מניין. bas aviv uvas imo minayin. How do I know
full sister? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar ערות בת אשת אביך מולדת אביך
אחותך היא. ervas bas eshes avicha moledes avicha achosecha hi. It says
that she's your sister. עד שלא יאמר ad shelo yomar יש לי
מן הדין. yesh li min hadin. So that I can't say I
can derive it from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מה אם הוזהר
על בת אמו שלא בת אביו ובת אביו שלא בת אמו. ma
im huzhar al bas imo shelo vas aviv uvas aviv shelo vas
imo. So I can say that the warning is against either the
half sister
who is the mother's daughter or the father's
daughter, ובת אביו שלא בת אמו. uvas aviv shelo vas imo. For
half sisters. So בת אביו ובת אמו לא כל שכן? bas aviv
uvas imo lo kol sheken? Couldn't I derive it that a full
sister should be from קל וחומר. kal vachomer. הא לא ענש אלא
שאין מוזהרין מן הדין.
ha lo anash ela
she'ein muzharin min hadin. And I learned it this way. even learn
not only אין עונשין מן הדין ein onshin min hadin that I
can't derive the punishment from קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but also you
can't even derive the אזהרה, azhara, the prohibition, from קל וחומר kal
vachomer for a capital crime. Okay, so חייבי מלקיות מנין, chayevei malkuyot
minayin, how do I know then about corporal crimes that receive only
מלקות? malkot? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, where do I learn it from?
רשע רשע. rasha rasha. I learn it from a גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah from the word רשע. rasha. That is the connection we mentioned
yesterday already, the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah that connects
מלקות malkot to capital punishment. So חייבי גלויות מנין, chayevei galuyot minayin,
how about for manslaughter cases that would go into exile? אתיא רוצח
רוצח. atya rotzeach rotzeach. It's learned from a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah
from the word רוצח, rotzeach, that a manslaughter is still called a
murderer and that connects him to a real murder case where he
would be a capital crime. So תניא אמר רבי יהודה בן טבאי,
tanya amar rabbi yehuda ben tavai,
sorry excuse me. Okay,
רבי
יהודה בן טבאי
rabbi yehuda
ben tavai said אראה בנחמה אם לא הרגתי עד זומם. ereh benechama
im lo haragti ed zomem. So רבי יהודה בן טבאי rabbi yehuda
ben tavai said אראה בנחמה, ereh benechama, like I should merit to
see the times of משיח, mashiach, that I didn't kill an עד
זומם ed zomem להוציא מלבן של צדוקים, lehotzi miliban shel tzedukim, to
contradict the opinion of the צדוקים, tzedukim, שהיו אומרים אין עדים זוממין
נהרגים עד שיהרג הנדון, shehayu omerim ein edim zomemin neheragim ad sheyehareg
hanidon, because the צדוקים tzedukim said that we should kill the עדים
זוממים... zomemim. we should not kill the עדים זוממים zomemim. only until
they kill the defendant. And therefore רבי יהודה בן טבאי rabbi yehuda
ben tavai said I actually executed... it's hard to parse I think.
I think he's saying that he actually killed the עד זומם ed
zomem in order even before the execution, and that's to contradict the
צדוקים. tzedukim. אמר לו שמעון בן שטח. amar lo shimon ben shetach.
So שמעון בן שטח shimon ben shetach said אראה בנחמה אם לא
שפכת דם נקי. ereh benechama im lo shafachta dam naki. But שמעון
בן שטח shimon ben shetach said like he swears that you didn't...
you did spill the innocent blood. שהרי אמרו חכמים אין עדים זוממין
נהרגים עד שיזומו שניהם. sheharei amru chachamim ein edim zomemin neheragim ad
sheyizomu sheneihem. Because the חכמים chachamim said עדים זוממים cannot be executed
until both of them are proven to be זוממים. ואין לוקין עד
שיזומו שניהם, ve'ein lokin ad sheyizomu sheneihem, and you can't give them
מלקות malkot until you prove that both of them are זוממים. מיד
קיבל עליו miyad kibel alav רבי יהודה בן טבאי rabbi yehuda ben
tavai שאינו מורה הוראה אלא לפני שמעון בן שטח. she'eino moreh hora'ah
ela lifnei shimon ben shetach.
So יהודה בן טבאי yehuda ben tavai
deferred to שמעון בן שטח's shimon ben shetach authority, that שמעון בן
שטח's shimon ben shetach opinion was even more above his. וכל ימיו
של רבי יהודה בן טבאי vechol yamav shel rabbi yehuda ben tavai
היה משתטח על קברו של אותו העד, haya mishtate'ach al kivro shel
oto ha'ed, and his whole life he would go do prostrations on
the grave of that witness, that עד זומם ed zomem who he
had killed because he didn't follow the opinion of שמעון בן שטח.
shimon ben shetach. והיה קולו נשמע, vehaya kolo nishma, and everyone heard
his voice crying. וכסבורים העם לומר קולו של ההרוג, ukasvurin ha'am lomar
kolo shel haharug, and they thought that it was the... that people
sort of made up an urban legend that it was the voice
of the one who was falsely put to death. אמר קולי שלי
הוא. amar koli sheli hu. So he said it's actually my voice.
תדעו למחר הוא מת אין קולו נשמע, ted'u l'machar hu met ein
kolo nishma, because they said whoever dies the next day he's not
going to be able to be heard. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה
דרבא לרב אשי. amar leh rav acha berei d'rava l'rav ashi. So
many hundreds of years later רב אחא rav acha the son of
רבא said to רב אשי, rav ashi, דילמא בדינא קם בהדיה אינמי
פיוסי פיוסיה. dilma bedina kam bahadeih inami piyusei piyuseih. So if
in such a case...
so even if it was בדינא קם בהדיה bedina kam bahadeih that
it was just that he went up against him, nonetheless he still
has room to פיוסי פיוסיה piyusei piyuseih to appease him. Okay so
that's a good place to stop. Gloria's going to pick up for
tomorrow's דף. daf. Everyone have a שבת שלום shabbat shalom and a
wonderful day. Bye bye.